A Finding Aid to the Robert Bruce Inverarity Papers, circa 1840s-1997, in the Archives of American Art AAA.inverobe
Archives of American Art
Robert Bruce Inverarity papers
circa 1840s-1997
AAA.inverobe
Archives of American Art
13.8 Cubic feet
The papers of artist, photographer, museum director, anthropologist, and writer Robert Bruce Inverarity are dated circa 1840s-1997 and measure 12.7 linear feet. Biographical information, correspondence, writings and notes, subject files, art work, scrapbooks, sound recordings, printed material and photographs are found within the papers. They document Inverarity's work as Director of the Federal Art Project in Seattle and Director of the Art and Craft Project for the State of Washington, as well as his other professional work. Nineteenth century material consists of a Japanese print, printed material, and photographs.
Inverarity, Robert Bruce
Biographical Note
Robert Bruce Inverarity (1909-1999) showed artistic leanings as a boy, and from an early age was fascinated by puppetry and Northwest Coast native culture. During much of his youth, Inverarity's family lived in Canada, but returned to their native Seattle when he was a teenager. After graduating from high school, he made a 500 mile journey on foot along the coasts of the Vancouver Islands, collecting Indian artifacts and studying the area's tribal legends.
He studied briefly with Mark Tobey in Seattle, where the two shared a studio; when Tobey departed for Chicago, Inverarity succeeded him as an art teacher at the Cornish School. He spent the next few years in California working as an artist, exhibiting, and occasionally teaching. From there, he moved to Vancouver where he was Director of the School of Creative Art. In 1932, Inverarity made a three month trip to the Queen Charlotte Islands, British Columbia, for the purpose of studying the Haida Indians.
Upon his return to the United States in 1933, Inverarity joined the University of Washington Drama School as a puppetry instructor; in 1938 he published a highly regarded Manual of Puppetry. During 1936-37, he took a leave of absence from the university to assume the position of State Director of the Federal Art Project, where he remained until 1939. He then became State Director of the Art and Crafts Project (1939-1941). The U.S. Navy appointed Inverarity Chief of Design for Camouflage (1941-1943) and he later served as an Official Navy War Artist (1943-1945).
During his early years as a teacher and administrator, Inverarity continued making art and participated in a wide variety of exhibitions. He published a portfolio, 12 Photographs by R. B. Inverarity (1940). In the following year, Movable Masks and Figures of the North Pacific Coast Indians, a portfolio of his watercolors reproduced as silkscreen prints, appeared. Although Inverarity stopped exhibiting in 1941, he continued to produce art; notable work of this period includes photographic portraits of a number of artist friends (Max Ernst, Dorothea Tanning, Marcel Duchamp, and Man Ray).
After World War II, Inverarity completed his formal education. He earned a Bachelor's degree in art and anthropology from the University of Washington (1946), and then studied with Hilaire Hiler at Freemont University in Los Angeles, where he was awarded a Master's degree in fine arts (1947) and a Ph.D. (1948).
Inverarity began his museum career in 1949 when he was appointed the first director of the Museum of International Folk Art in Santa Fe, New Mexico, a position that combined his interest in, and knowledge of, anthropology and art. While in Santa Fe, he published Art of the North West Coast Indians (1950). During his five year tenure as director, the museum participated in a pilot study for coding visual files, a project of the anthropological group, Human Resources Area Files, Inc. When Inverarity was dismissed from the Museum of International Folk Art in 1954, most of the staff resigned in protest, and the American Association of Museums investigated the situation.
Inverarity then became the first director of the Adirondack Museum, Blue Mountain Lake, New York, where he remained for eleven years. In addition to planning the museum's building, and developing collections and programs, Inverarity continued his involvement with the visual files project of the Human Resources Area Files, Inc., studying information storage and retrieval, developing a "microreader," and publishing Visual Files Coding Index (1960). In addition, he published many articles on a variety of topics and was active in organizations for anthropologists and museum professionals.
After his 1965 departure from the Adirondack Museum, Inverarity went to California and worked as an illustrator and book designer at the University of California Press. He returned to the east coast in 1969 to assume the directorship of the Philadelphia Maritime Museum. During this period, he remained active in professional associations and traveled to study museums abroad. He retired in 1976 and moved to La Jolla, California.
Robert Bruce Inverarity died in 1999.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of artist, photographer, museum director, anthropologist, and writer Robert Bruce Inverarity are dated circa 1840s-1997 and measure 13.8 linear feet. Biographical information, correspondence, writings and notes, subject files, art work, scrapbooks, sound recordings, printed material and photographs are found within the papers. They document Inverarity's work as Director of the Federal Art Project in Seattle and Director of the Art and Craft Project for the State of Washington, as well as his other professional work. Nineteenth century material consists of a Japanese print, printed material, and photographs.
Among the biographical information are awards and certificates, biographical and genealogical notes, and educational records. Correspondence concerns Inverarity's activities as Director of the WPA Federal Arts Project in Washington State, 1936-1941. Additional personal and professional correspondence, 1929-1993, documents his activities as a museum director, consultant, collector, and writer. Among the friends and colleagues with whom he corresponded are: Max Ernst and Dorothea Tanning, Rockwell and Sally Kent, Stanton MacDonald-Wright, Wolfgang Palen, Juliet and Man Ray, Mark Tobey, Edward Weston, and various individuals associated with the WPA.
Manuscripts of a few of Inverarity's many articles on topics such as anthropology, museology, and information storage and retrieval are among his writings and notes. Also included are the manuscript of an unpublished book, Tobey Remembered, along with drafts, notes, correspondence, research materials, and photocopies of Tobey's letters to him and others. Other writings consist of book reviews, children's books, a catalog of the Inverarity Collection, and a copy of his 1946 master's thesis, "The Social-Economic Position of the American Artist." Several journals, 1928-1966, survive, including one that records his 1932 trip to study the Haida Indians of the Queen Charlotte Islands.
Subject files include general subjects such as "Folk Art" and "Preservation." Files on the museums where Inverarity was the director contain some official records as well as general information. Art work by Inverarity includes eight volumes of sketch books, 1928-1942, commercial work for Boeing, notes and drawings for book designs. Among the work by other artists are drawings, paintings and prints by friends. Of particular interest are display panels for a small exhibit on airbrush stencil prints produced by the Washington State WPA Federal Art Project. Other noteworthy items are pencil sketches and a watercolor by Mark Tobey, and prints by Hiroshige and Jan Matulka.
Five scrapbooks, 1928-1979, contain newspaper clippings, miscellaneous printed items, and a small number of photographs and letters. Three volumes document his career as an artist and museum director. One consists of biographical information and items designed by Inverarity, and another concerns publication and marketing of his monograph Art of the Northwest Coast Indians.
Sound recordings consist of interviews and conversations. An extensive interview with Inverarity about his life and career was conducted by Craig Gilborn in 1990. Bruce and Jane Inverarity in conversation with former colleague Ernie Johnson and his wife Helen about his departure from the Museum of International Folk Art were recorded in 1980. Also included is a 1981 conversation with Grace T. Stevenson containing references to Mark Tobey and Morris Graves.
Printed material includes many items about or produced by the WPA Federal Art Project. Among the items written by Inverarity are many articles on a wide variety of topics, his book Art of the Northwest Coast Indians, and two published portfolios. Printed material by other authors includes articles, books and reports about or mentioning Inverarity, and books designed or illustrated by him. Among the miscellaneous printed items are catalogs and brochures of the schools where Inverarity taught and studied, and a few ephemeral items designed by him.
Photographs are of art work, people, places, the Washington State WPA Federal Art Project, and miscellaneous subjects. All photographs known to be by Inverarity are clearly marked. Art work includes views of Inverarity's collection of his own work and that of other artists hanging in his home. Photographs of people include artists, friends, colleagues, and various groups. Of special interest are Inverarity's portraits of artists, among them Marcel Duchamp, Max Ernst, Morris Graves, Hilaire Hiler, Rico Le Brun, Stanton MacDonald-Wright, Man Ray, Dorothea Tanning, and Mark Tobey. Photographs of places include the museums where Inverarity was director, places in which he lived, and travel pictures. Of note are a large group of photographs (copy prints) taken in 1932 while studying the Haida Indians in British Columbia. Nineteenth century photographs of family homes, Europe, and South America may have been taken by his father. Photographs of the Washington State WPA Federal Arts Project are of individual works of art, exhibition installations, mosaic procedures and local art centers. Many, probably intended for display, are mounted in groups on large cardboard panels. Miscellaneous subjects include art photographs by Inverarity and the microreader he invented.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as nine series. Correspondence is in chronological order, Biographical Information and Subject Files are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Other series have been organized into subseries and arrangement is as described in the Series Descriptions/Container List below. Unless noted otherwise, material within folders is arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1934-1997, undated (Box 1, OV 18; 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1928-1993, undated (Box 1; 0.75 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1928-1993, undated, (Boxes 2-3; 1.5 linear ft.)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1938-1990, undated (Boxes 3-6, OV19-20; 2.5 linear ft.)
Series 5: Art Work, circa 1840s-1969, undated (Boxes 6, 12, 16, OV 21; 1.3 linear ft.)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1928-1991, undated (Boxes 7-8; 1.1 linear ft.)
Series 7: Sound Recordings, 1980-1990 (Box 8; 3 folders)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1902-1995, undated (Boxes 8-11, 13, OV 22; 3.4 linear ft.)
Series 9: Photographs, circa 1870s-1990, undated (Boxes 11, 14-17, OV 23; 3.0 linear ft.)
Provenance
Robert Bruce Inverarity donated his papers to the Archives in several installments between 1965 and 1993. Additional papers were received from his estate in 1999. He also loaned a small number of additional drawings and sketches for microfilming which were returned to him. A few of these drawings were included with the papers he subsequently donated to the Archives of American Art.
Separated Material
Originals of most of the drawings and sketches loaned by Mr. Inverarity were returned to him after filming and were not subsequently donated. This material is available on 35 mm microfilm reel D/NDA/I, frames 392-409.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
A portion of the collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 1121, 1130, D/NDA/I and NDA-16 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Deutsch, Hilda, 1911-; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968 -- Photographs; Federal Art Project (Calif.); Federal Art Project (Ill.); Federal Art Project (Iowa); Federal Art Project (N.Y.); Federal Art Project (Or.); Federal Art Project (Utah); Federal Art Project (Wash.); Graves, Morris, 1910- -- Photographs; Morris, Carl, 1911-1993; Museum of International Folk Art (N.M.); Ray, Man, 1890-1976 -- Photographs; Tobey, Mark; Art and state--Washington (State); Arts administrators; Drawings; Federal aid to the arts--Washington (State); Interviews; New Deal, 1933-1939--Washington (State); Painters; Photographs; Puppet theater; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; United States--Economic conditions, 1918-1945--Washington (State); Works of art
- Biographical Information, 1934-1997, undated; Series 1; (Box 1, OV 18; 0.25 linear ft.)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1934-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, Jane Inverarity (wife), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Notes, Robert Bruce Inverarity, 1957-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Driver's License, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Educational Records, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Genealogical Notes, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Identification Badges, U.S. Navy and U.S. Coast Guard, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership Cards, 1934-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Selective Service Registration, 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1947 and 1959 (Box OV 16)
- Correspondence, 1928-1993, undated; Series 2; (Box 1; 0.75 linear ft.)
  Scope and Contents note
  Personal correspondence regarding Inverarity's activities as Washington State director of the WPA Federal Art Project, 1936-1941, along with other correspondence from the same period not directly relating to the WPA and miscellaneous undated correspondence, has been microfilmed on Reel NDA-16. Additional personal and professional correspondence, 1929-1993 and undated has not been microfilmed. Among this correspondence are a very small number of letters addressed to his wife, Jane. Correspondents include their daughter, friends, and colleagues, among them: Max Ernst, Dorothea Tanning, Rockwell and Sally Kent, Stanton Macdonald-Wright, Wolfgang Palen, Juliet and Man Ray, Mark Tobey, Edward Weston, and various individuals associated with the W.P.A. Business correspondence concerns appraisals and consulting work, publications, conferences, the Museum of International Folk Art, the Adirondack Museum, and the Philadelphia Maritime Museum.
  Please note that many subject files (Series 4) also contain correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1936-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-14)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-21)
  - Carr, Emily, 1928-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dunn, Kwei, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ernst, Max and Dorothea Tanning, 1945-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Kent, Rockwell and Sally (later, Sally Kent Gorton), 1945-1988 (Box 1, Folder 25-28)
  - MacDonald-Wright, Stanton, 1941-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Palen, Wolfgang, 1943-1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Ray, Man and Juliet, 1950-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sapiro, Scotty, 1986-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Tobey, Mark, 1928-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Weston, Edward, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - W.P.A. (Holger Cahill, Dan Deffenbacher, Hilda Deutsch, Carl Morris, et al), 1938-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Writings and Notes, 1928-1993, undated; Series 3; (Boxes 2-3; 1.5 linear ft)
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  3.1: By Inverarity, 1928-1989, undated
  3.2: By Other Authors, 1947-1993
  - By Inverarity, 1928-1989, undated; 3.1
    - Articles, A-Z (by title) (Box 2)
      - "Florence Dibble Bartlett,", 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Haida,", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - "The Museum of International Folk Art, Santa Fe, New Mexico,", 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - "A New Structuralization for Organization of Visual Records,", 1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - "Phuket" (by J. and R. B. Inverarity), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - "Preservation of Water-Submerged, Partially Decayed Boats by Chemical Impregnation" (by Ray M. Seborg and Robert B. Inverarity), circa 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - "Reading Microreproduction by Optical Magnification,", undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - "A Simplified Technique for Recording Museum Survey Data" (published in The Museologist), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - "Temples of Pagan,", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - "Thoughts on the Organization of Museums" (published in Curator), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Untitled Article about Basket Maker "Spike" Draper (with photographs), 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Untitled Articles about Mark Tobey (with notes), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Untitled Articles about Trip to Queen Charlotte Islands to Study the Haida in 1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Untitled Articles (published and unpublished; various topics), 1958-1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Untitled Fragment, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Book, Tobey Remembered (Box 2)
      - Manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Illustrations, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Draft 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
      - Draft 2, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Correspondence with Researchers and Publishers, 1971-1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Letters from Mark Tobey (photocopies), 1928-1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Letters from Mark Tobey and Letters mentioning Tobey (typescript copies), 1928-1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Letters from Mark Tobey to Grace T. Stevenson (photocopies), 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Notes, 1968, 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - "Possible Illustrations" and Design Ideas (includes original photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Research Material (printed), 1940-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Book Reviews (with related correspondence), 1958-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Catalog, Notes Regarding the Inveraity Collection in the Museum of Mankind... (Box 2)
      - Manuscript, circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Drafts, circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
      - Notes, circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Children's Books (with illustrations), 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
    - Journals (Box 3)
      - Journal, 1928-1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Journal and Notes of Trip to Queen Charlotte Islands, Canada, to Study the Haida Indians, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Journal Recording End of Tenure at Adirondack Museum, April 1965-January 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
      - Color and Composition, 1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Inventions (with diagrams), 1955-1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1954-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Reports (Box 3)
      - European Museum Survey, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - "The Fred Archer School of Photography,", 1947 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - "Report to the Axel-Wenner Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research of a Brief Trip to the Scandinavian Countries and Other Part of Europe, June to July 1951,", 1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - "Summary Report, 'Visual Files Pilot Project,' to Board of Directors of the Human Relations Area Files, Inc.,", 1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Talks and Lectures, 1952-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Thesis for M.F.A., University of Scientific Method, Los Angeles, "The Social-Economic Position of the American Artist... A Brief Survey,", 1946 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - By Other Authors, 1947-1993; 3.2
    - Cohea, Carol. "Florence Dibble Bartlett" (Women in New Mexico project), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Hodge, F. W. Foreword to Art of the Northwest Coast Indians by Robert Bruce Inverarity, circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Ray, May. Lecture (transcript), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Sanches, José Benito. "The Life and Death of the First World" and "The Gods Come to Life on Earth" (text for exhibition labels), 1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Whitlock, Katherine. Research Paper on Dr. Bruce Inverarity, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Subject Files, 1938-1990, undated; Series 4; (Boxes 3-6, OV 19-20; 2.5 linear ft.)
  Subject files, compiled for reference and research purposes, include a variety of printed material, photographs, correspondence and notes.
  - Adirondack Museum, 1955-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Arizona Pioneers' Historical Society, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Cogswell Collection Appraisal, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Columbia University/Sackler Foundation Symposium, "Early Chinese Art and Its Possible Influence in the Pacific Basin,", 1966-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Folk Art, 1949-1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Fred Archer School of Photography, 1947-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Information Storage and Retrieval (Box 4)
    - "Adirondack Museum Punchcard System I Developed for Photos,", circa 1954-1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - General Information (printed material), 1950s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 2-8)
    - Microviewer (invented by Inverarity), 1952-1964, undated (Box 4, Folder 9-12)
    - Visual Files Project (Human Relations Area Files, Inc.), 1950-1963 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - Inverarity Collection (Box 4)
    - "Collection Data, Dealers, etc.,", 1950-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Consignments and Sales, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "Notes Regarding the Inverarity Collection in the Museum of Mankind, The Ethnography Department at the British Museum, London, England," by Robert Bruce Inverarity, circa 1978 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Photographs and Catalog Information (bound volume), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Printed Material, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kent, Rockwell, 1964-1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lake George Boats and Ships (historical reference file), 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Museum of International Folk Art (Box 5)
    - Clippings, General, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Clippings re: Death of Florence Dibble Bartlett, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Clippings re: Inverarity's Dismissal, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1959 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
    - History, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Notes, 1949-1955, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Printed Material, 1953, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Reports, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Visual Files Pilot Project (Human Relations Area Files, Inc.), 1951-1953; (see also: Information Storage and Retrieval, Visual Files Project) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Museum of Navajo Ceremonial Art, 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Peruvian Collection Purchased by Inverarity and Ralph Altman (photographs are by Inverarity), 1948 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Philadelphia Maritime Museum (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Gazela Primeiro, 1970-1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Notes on Gallery Installation (with sketches), 1970s (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Publicity and General Information, 1969-1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Reports, 1969-1976 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Photography (Box 5)
    - General Information (printed material), 1985-1990, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Lists and Notes, 1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
    - Releases, 1938-1983 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Rights and Reproductions, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 28)